Register of the Pasternak Family Papers, 1877-2012
Hoover Institution Archives
Pasternak family papers,
1877-2012
96063
Hoover Institution Archives
156 manuscript boxes, 24 oversize boxes, 4 card file boxes, 1 phonotape cassette, 1 videotape cassette, digital files (94.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, diaries, memoirs, other writings, biographical data, printed matter, drawings, photographs, and other audiovisual material relating to Russian art and literature, culture in the Soviet Union, and Russian émigré life. Includes papers of Leonid and Rosalia Pasternak; their sons, the poet and novelist Boris Pasternak and architect and memoirist Aleksandr Pasternak; their daughters, Josephine Pasternak and Lydia Pasternak Slater; and other family members.
Pasternak family
Access
Boxes 37 and 44-49 may not be used without permission of the Archivist. Use photocopies available.
Boxes 53-59 are closed. Digital use copies available.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1996, 2004, and 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
In part, also available on microfilm (55 reels).
Scope and Content Note
The Pasternak family papers consist of material formerly in the possession of Josephine Pasternak and Lydia Pasternak Slater, the sisters of the poet and Nobel Prize winner Boris Pasternak. This material has been arranged into series corresponding to each member of the Pasternak family, including the poet's parents, Leonid and Rosalia, his sisters, Josephine Pasternak and Lydia Pasternak Slater, and his younger brother, Aleksandr. All but Boris and Aleksandr emigrated to Germany and subsequently to England after the 1917 Russian revolution.
The resulting intimate correspondence, dating from the 1920s and 1930s, between Boris Pasternak, his parents, and his sisters is of primary importance. Also of interest are Josephine and Lydia's extensive correspondence with Pasternak literary scholars, family, and friends. The bulk of the collection concerns the work of Leonid Pasternak, a famous painter, and Josephine's and Lydia's efforts to preserve and publicize his legacy both in the Soviet Union and abroad. Included in this part are the artist's drawings and sketches, as well as working material and manuscripts prepared for the publication of his memoirs. Also of interst are Lydia Pasternak Slater's writings in Russian, German, and English and her translations.
Olga Freidenberg, a niece of Leonid Pasternak, kept diaries/memoirs that give a full account of her school and university years, scholarly life, and the tragic siege of Leningrad, where she and her mother were living.
The smaller archive related to Rosalia Kaufman-Pasternak, a well-known classical pianist, gives interesting insights into the world of Russian music in the years just before the revolution.
The collection also includes materials from Lydia's children and Boris's son, Evgenii Pasternak.
As a whole, the collection gives a valuable glimpse into the artistic and cultural life of Russia from the 1880s to the late 1970s as seen in the life and work of a multi-faceted and talented family.
Pasternak, Boris Leonidovich,1890-1960.; Pasternak, Leonid Osipovich, 1862-1945.; Pasternak, Zh. L. (Zhozefina Leonidovna); Art--Russia.; Drawings.; Phonotapes.; Russia.; Russian literature.; Russians in foreign countries.; Soviet Union--Civilization.; Soviet Union.; Video tapes.
- LEONID PASTERNAK FILE, 1885-1990 (Box 1-11)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material, correspondence, notebooks and portfolios of drawings and miscellaneous material related to the exhibit and sale of his work; writings and other material used in the preparation of his memoirs; Russian and English drafts of the memoirs prepared by Josephine Pasternak; critical material and writings about Leonid Pasternak, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Includes photocopies of correspondence from Marina TSvetaeva (originals in RESTRICTED SERIES).
  - Biographical material. See also JOSEPHINE PASTERNAK FILE (Box 1)
    - General, Miscellaneous notes re genealogy of the Pasternak family. Handwritten, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Recommendation from Maksimova (wife of Nikolai Maksimov), Holograph, 1885 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Receipt from Louise Maude for illustrations to Lev Tolstoy's Resurrection, Photocopy, 1902 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Affidavit from Narodnyi Komissariat po prosveshcheniiu signed by A. Lunacharskii re circumstances of Leonid Pasternak's going abroad, Typescript, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Permit granted by the Narodnyi Komissariat po prosveshcheniiu to take abroad works of art listed in document, Typescript, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Financial agreement re "Ursula" painting, Berlin, Typescript, 1929 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Visiting card, 1920s (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Work permit, Great Britain. Home Office. Typescript, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Testament, Holograph, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Clippings
    - Art. Includes articles about his art and reviews of exhibits
      - General, 1889-1917 (Box-folder 1: 10-12)
      - English (Box-folder 1: 13-14)
      - German
        - General (Box-folder 1: 15)
        - 1924-1929 (Box-folder 1: 16)
        - 1932-1942 (Box-folder 1: 17)
      - Russian (Box-folder 1: 18-19)
      - Miscellany (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - Memoirs. Includes excerpts published in the periodical press and reviews
      - English (Box-folder 1: 21)
      - German (Box-folder 1: 22)
      - Russian (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Incoming
      - General
        - 1925-1937 (Box-folder 2: 1)
        - 1938-1942 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      - Barou, N., 1941 (Box-folder 2: 3)
      - Braz, O., 1929-1936 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Corinth, Lovis, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 5)
      - Deutsche Bücherei, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 6)
      - Ehrenburg, Il'ia and Liubov, undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
      - Ettinger, Pavel, Includes letters of condolence at Leonid Pasternak's death, 1930-1945 (Box-folder 2: 8)
      - Freidenberg, Ol'ga, 1920s?-1929 (Box-folder 2: 9)
      - Liebermann, Max, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 10)
      - Lob, Martha, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 2: 11)
      - Lur'e, B., 1943 (Box-folder 2: 12)
      - L'vov, Aleksei, 1932-1936 (Box-folder 2: 13)
      - Maiskii, Agniia and Vasilii, See also Soviet Union. Posol'stvo (Great Britain), 1943 (Box-folder 2: 14)
      - Pasternak, Evgeniia, Includes letters to all members of the Pasternak family, 1927-1931 (Box-folder 2: 15)
      - Pasternak, Fedor and Josephine
        - Undated (Box-folder 2: 16)
        - 1921-1930 (Box-folder 2: 17)
      - Pasternak, Lydia, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 18)
      - Polenov, Nikolai, 1928 (Box-folder 2: 19)
      - Remizov, Aleksei, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 20)
      - Repin, Il'ia, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 2: 21)
      - Samuel, Herbert, 1924-1938 (Box-folder 2: 22)
      - Serova, Nataliia, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 23)
      - Serova, Ol'ga, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 2: 24)
      - Shaliapin, Fedor, 1929 (Box-folder 2: 25)
      - Société du Musée Léon Tolstoï, 1909 (Box-folder 2: 26)
      - Soiuz Russkikh Khudozhnikov, undated (Box-folder 2: 27)
      - Soviet Union. Posol'stvo (Great Britain), Includes letters from and drafts of answers to Vasilii Zonov and S. Rostovskii, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 2: 28)
      - Struck, Hermann, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 2: 29)
      - Sukhotina-Tolstaia, Tatiana, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 2: 30)
      - Tolstoy, Lev, Holograph and typescript copies, 1904 (Box-folder 2: 31)
      - TSvetaeva, Marina, Includes draft of answer in Rosalia Pasternak's hand and explanatory note by Josephine Pasternak, 1922-1928 (Box-folder 2: 32)
      - Vinogradov, Sergei, 1923-1930 (Box-folder 2: 33)
      - Zonov, Vasilii. Ambassador of the U.S.S.R. to Great Britain. See Soviet Union. Posol'stvo (Great Britain)
    - Outgoing
      - Surname unknown, 1923-1944 (Box-folder 2: 34)
      - Uchilishche ZHivopisi, Vaianiia I Zodchestva, undated (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Critical material and writings about Leonid Pasternak
    - General
      - General. Miscellaneous short biographies
        - Printed (Box-folder 2: 36)
        - Typescript (Box-folder 2: 37)
      - "Jacobs Segen." Review of Rembrandt exhibit. Printed proof, n.d (Box-folder 2: 38)
      - "Professor Pasternak on the Jewish Art Expedition," P.T.A. Bulletin, Mimeograph, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 39)
    - Ben-Jischai, A., "Mit Leonid Pasternak in Jerusalem," Holograph, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 40)
    - Bialik, Hayyim, draft of "Monographie," Holograph, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 41)
    - Buckman, David, Leonid Pasternak: A Russian Impressionist, Maltzahn Gallery Ltd., Printed copy, 1974 (Box-folder 2: 42)
    - Bulgakov, V., "L. O. Pasternak," Iskusstvo, Clipping, 1961 (Box-folder 2: 43)
    - Gibian, George, "Doctor Zhivago, Russia, and Leonid Pasternak's Rembrandt," Printed copy. See also JOSEPHINE PASTERNAK FILE, Correspondence with Rimgaila Salys for commentary, 1983 (Box-folder 2: 44)
    - Gurdus, Luba, "The Forgotten Friendship: L.O. Pasternak and A.J. Stybel," The First Jewish Art Annual, Printed copy. Includes annotations by Josephine Pasternak, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 45)
    - Mallac, Guy de, "A Russian Impressionist: Leonid Osipovich Pasternak, 1862-1945," California Slavic Studies, Printed copy, 1977 (Box-folder 2: 46)
    - Osborn, Max, "Leonid Pasternak," Typescript and printed copy, undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Parrott, Cecil
      - General
        - "Leonid Pasternak," with a preface by Josephine Pasternak, Typescript draft, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
        - "Russian Landscape Painting," Typescript of lecture, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 3)
      - Plays produced by the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), Typescript, 1975
        - "Leonid and Rosa Pasternak" (Box-folder 3: 4)
        - "The Moscow Merchants" (Box-folder 3: 5)
        - "The Pasternaks: A Family Portrait" (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Pasternak, Josephine
      - Short biographies, Typescript, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
      - "Pasternak in Oxford," Oxford Art Journal, Printed copy, 1978
      - "L. O. Pasternak," Bol'shoi Sovetskii Entsyklopedicheskii Slovar', supplementary material for biographical article on Leonid Pasternak, Typescript drafts, 1984
        - English (Box-folder 3: 8)
        - Russian (Box-folder 3: 9)
      - "Nachbemerkung zum Geleitbriefe," Typescript, 1986 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Rodzinski, Stanislaw, "Leonid Pasternak: Thoughts About Art," Biuletyn, English translation of Polish article. Typescript, 1978 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - Salys, Rimgaila, "Exhibiting in Russia at the Turn of the Century: Leonid Pasternak between ", 1888 and 1916
      - Draft with annotations by Josephine Pasternak, Typescript, 1985 (Box-folder 3: 12)
      - Festschrift in Honor of Kenneth Lindsay, Printed copy, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Struck, German, "Professor Leonid Pasternak," Includes holograph English, typescript Russian, and printed German version, undated (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Swet, Gershon, "Pamiati L. Pasternaka," Vestnik Izraelia, Clipping and typescript in Russian and German, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Drawings and paintings
    - Lists of drawings and paintings, Includes short descriptions, history of ownership, and location of exhibits and individual works. Also includes lists of items for sale, undated (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Notebooks
      - General. Sketches in pencil. Includes annotations and drafts of letters, some dated, 1930s (Box-folder 3: 17-20)
      - General. Sketches in pencil. Includes annotations and drafts of letters, some dated, 1930s (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
      - Trip to Palestine. Sketches in colored chalk (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Portfolio. Sketches in pencil, undated (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Exhibits and sales file
    - General
      - Germany
        - Internationaler Kunstmarkt Düsseldorf. Invitation, 1976 (Box-folder 4: 5)
        - Kunsthandlung Victor Hartberg, Berlin
          - 1927-1928
            - Program (Box-folder 4: 6)
            - Reviews. Clippings (Box-folder 4: 7)
          - Invitation to seventieth birthday retrospective, 1932 (Box-folder 4: 8)
        - Städtische Galerie im Lenbachhaus, München, Leonid Pasternak: Studien und Zeichnungen, catalog, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Great Britain
        - Ashmolean Museum, Oxford
          - 1958
            - Catalog, Memorial Exhibition of Paintings and Drawings by Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945. Printed copy (Box-folder 4: 10)
            - List of individuals receiving catalogs. Typescript (Box-folder 4: 11)
          - Catalog and program, 1990 (Box-folder 4: 12)
        - City Art Galleries, Sheffield, Schedule of exhibits and review, 1978 (Box-folder 4: 13)
        - Crawford Center for the Arts, University of St. Andrew's
          - Catalog, Leonid Pasternak. 1862-1945, 1978 (Box-folder 4: 14)
          - List of works exhibited (Box-folder 4: 15)
        - Ely House, London, 1969
          - Catalog, Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945 (Box-folder 4: 16)
          - Invitation (Box-folder 4: 17)
        - Herbert Art Gallery and Museum, Coventry, 1962
          - Catalog, Leonid Pasternak. (Box-folder 4: 18)
          - Typescript draft and printed copy
          - List of invitations (Box-folder 4: 19)
        - Little Malvern Priory, Worcester, Clippings, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 20)
        - Maltzahn Gallery Limited, London, 1974
          - Clippings, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 4: 21)
          - Contract between Maltzahn Gallery Limited, Josephine Pasternak and Lydia Pasternak Slater, Typescript copy, 1976 (Box-folder 4: 22)
          - Invitations (Box-folder 4: 23)
        - Museum of Modern Art, Oxford, 1983
          - Catalog, Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945. Typescript drafts and printed copy (Box-folder 4: 24)
          - Invitation (Box-folder 4: 25)
          - Poster (Box-folder 4: 26)
        - Pushkin Club, London, Program and invitation to exhibit as well as to lecture by Josephine Pasternak, 1958 (Box-folder 4: 27)
        - Sotheby's. Catalogue of Russian Paintings, Drawings, Watercolours and Sculpture, 1981 (Box-folder 4: 28)
        - Talbot Rice Art Center, University of Edinburgh, Announcement and clippings of reviews, 1978 (Box-folder 4: 29)
        - Taliesin Arts Centre, University College of Swansea, Invitation, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 30)
      - Israel - Art Gallery Leivik House, Tel-Aviv, List of paintings and drawings exhibited. Typescript, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 31)
      - Soviet Union
        - Gosudarstvennyi Muzei Izobrazitel'nogo Iskusstva, Pasternak, Evgenii, introduction to catalog. Typescript, 1993 (Box-folder 4: 32)
        - Gosudarstvennaia Tret'iakovskaia galereia, 1979
          - Program (Box-folder 4: 33)
          - Radio broadcast transcript. Typescript (Box-folder 4: 34)
          - Miscellany (Box-folder 4: 35)
        - Gosudarstvennyi muzei L. N. Tolstogo, "L. N. Pasternak--illiustrator L. N. Tolstogo." Printed program, 1972 (Box-folder 4: 36)
        - Obshchestvo kollektionerov, Levitin, typescript draft of introduction to the exhibit, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 37)
        - Tsentral'nyi Dom khudozhnika, Miscellaneous printed matter, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 38)
      - United States - Smithsonian Institution Traveling Exhibition Services, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
        - Catalog. A Russian Impressionist: Paintings and Drawings by Leonid Pasternak, 1890-1945, Printed copy, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 1)
        - Legal agreement. Typescript (Box-folder 5: 2)
        - Printed matter. "Leonid Pasternak: Paintings and Drawings, 1880-1940," Update, 1986 (Box-folder 5: 3)
        - Programs and invitations, Meridian House International (Box-folder 5: 4)
        - Reviews. Clippings (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Correspondence, mostly of Josephine Pasternak. See JOSEPHINE PASTERNAK FILE, Correspondence
    - Miscellany. Includes catalogues of exhibits displaying works by Leonid Pasternak (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Writings
    - General
      - "Iz neopublikovannykh tekstov L. O. Pasternaka," text prepared by Josephine Pasternak, Typescript draft, undated (Box-folder 5: 7)
      - "Moi vospominaniia o Tolstom. Kak sozdavalos' 'Voskresenie'," Holograph, undated (Box-folder 5: 8)
      - "München und Die Münchener Akademie," Typescript, undated (Box-folder 5: 9)
      - "V. D. Polenov: Iz moikh vospominanii," Holograph, 1928 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - Letters to the editor
      - "Pis'mo khudizhnika L. O. Pasternaka," Lebed', Printed copy, 1909 (Box-folder 5: 11)
      - Untitled, The Daily Telegraph, Printed copy, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Memoirs of Leonid Pasternak
      - Published excerpts
        - "My Meetings With Tolstoy"
          - Mediterranean Review, Also includes typescript draft, 1970 (Box-folder 5: 15)
          - Russian Review, Reprint, 1960 (Box-folder 5: 16)
        - "Under a Listless Star," The Yale Literary Magazine, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 17)
        - Printed copies
          - The Memoirs of Leonid Pasternak, translated by Jennifer Bradshaw, with an introduction by Josephine Pasternak, Quartet Books, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 13)
          - Zapisi raznykh let, Sovetskii khudozhnik, 1975 (Box-folder 5: 14)
      - Working material. Miscellaneous material related to Leonid Pasternak used by Josephine Pasternak in preparing the text of his memoirs (Box 6)
        - Clippings from Russian newspapers, 1910-1916 (Box-folder 6: 1)
        - Notebooks, undated
          - Holograph in Leonid Pasternak's hand
            - 1-2 (Box-folder 6: 2)
            - 3-5 (Box-folder 6: 3)
            - 6-7 (Box-folder 6: 4)
        - Holograph in Leonid Pasternak's hand or dictated by him to Josephine Pasternak. Includes some drawings (Box-folder 6: 5-11)
        - Notes in Leonid and Josephine Pasternak's hand, undated (Box-folder 7: 1-9)
      - Drafts prepared by Josephine Pasternak, undated
        - Russian
          - General. "Materialy k biografii L. O. Pasternaka: Vvedenie"
            - Holograph (Box-folder 7: 10)
            - Typescript (Box-folder 7: 11)
          - Notebooks
            - 1-97 (Box-folder 7: 12)
            - 98-203 (Box-folder 7: 13)
            - 204-303 (Box-folder 7: 14)
            - 304-394 (Box-folder 7: 15)
            - 395-495 (Box-folder 8: 1)
            - 496-594 (Box-folder 8: 2)
            - 595-693 (Box-folder 8: 3)
            - 694-853 (Box-folder 8: 4)
            - 854-1011 (Box-folder 8: 5)
            - Index (Box-folder 8: 6)
          - Typescript text
            - General (Box-folder 8: 7)
            - General (Box-folder 9: 1-3)
            - Final manuscript prepared by Josephine Pasternak and edited by Aleksandr and Lydia Pasternak-Slater, undated (Box-folder 9: 4-12)
        - English (Box 10)
          - General
            - "Material for the Biography, and Work of L. Pasternak," from the archives of the Tretiakov Gallery in Moscow, 1950s (Box-folder 10: 1)
            - "Meetings with Tolstoy" (Box-folder 10: 2)
            - "Notes By Leonid Pasternak" (described as unsatisfactory English)
              - Draft I
                - 47-115 (Box-folder 10: 3)
                - 116-150 (Box-folder 10: 4)
                - 151-195 (Box-folder 10: 5)
              - Draft II
                - 1-150 (Box-folder 10: 6)
                - 151-314 (Box-folder 10: 7)
                - 316-425 (Box-folder 10: 8)
            - Introduction (Box-folder 10: 9)
            - Chapter 4 (Box-folder 10: 10)
          - Notebooks containing drafts of translations of material related to Leonid Pasternak by Josephine Pasternak, Handwritten, 1950s (Box-folder 11: 1-4)
          - Miscellany. Includes bibliography of Leonid Pasternak's works, Handwritten, undated (Box-folder 11: 5)
- Rosalia KAUFMAN PASTERNAK FILE, 1878-1911 (Box 11)
  Biographical material related to her musical career, including programs and reviews of her concerts in Odessa and Moscow, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General (Box 11)
    - Bachmann, D., Rosa Koffmann: Eine biographische Efizze, Odessa, 1885
      - Manuscript, 1884 (Box-folder 11: 6)
      - Photocopy of printed edition (Box-folder 11: 7)
    - Levitsky, Serge, "Rose Koffmann-Pasternak: La mère du poète," Slavic and East European Studies, Clipping, undated (Box-folder 11: 8)
    - Pasternak, Josephine, reminiscences, Typescript draft, undated (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - Musical career
    - General. Imperatorskoe Russkoe Muzykal'noe Obshchestvo, schedule of examinations, Odessa, 1889 (Box-folder 11: 10)
    - Concerts
      - Programs
        - Odessa, 1889 (Box-folder 11: 11)
        - Moscow, 1895-1911 (Box-folder 11: 12)
      - Reviews
        - Odessa, 1878-1881 (Box-folder 11: 13)
        - Moscow, 1895-1910 (Box-folder 11: 14)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 11: 15)
- BORIS PASTERNAK FILE, 1912-1992 (Box 11-13)
  Clippings, conference file, critical material, writings, and photocopies (originals in RESTRICTED SERIES) of correspondence of Boris Pasternak with Leonid, Rosalia, Josephine, and Fedor Pasternak and with Lydia Pasternak-Slater, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Clippings (Box 11)
    - English, 1958-1988 (Box-folder 11: 16-19)
    - German, 1958-1990 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Russian, 1962-1990 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - Conference file
    - "Boris Pasternak Centenary Conference," Oxford, 1990
      - Correspondence of Helen Ramsay
        - General, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 12: 3)
        - Barnes, Christopher, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 12: 4)
      - Program (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - "Boris Pasternak Centenary Exhibition," South Bank Centre, Miscellany, including programs and invitation, 1990 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - "Boris Pasternak Centennial," Stanford University, Printed program, 1990 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - "Pasternakovskie chteniia: Materialy mezhvuzovskoi konferentsii," Perm', Printed copy, 1990 (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - Correspondence with Leonid, Rosalia, Josephine, Lydia and Fedor Pasternak. Photocopies. Originals in RESTRICTED SERIES
    - Undated (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - 1921 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - 1924 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - 1925 (Box-folder 12: 12)
    - 1926 (Box-folder 12: 13-14)
    - 1927 (Box-folder 12: 15)
    - 1928 (Box-folder 12: 16)
    - 1929 (Box-folder 12: 17)
    - 1930 (Box-folder 12: 18)
    - 1931 (Box-folder 12: 19)
    - 1932 (Box-folder 12: 20)
    - 1933 (Box-folder 12: 21)
    - 1934 (Box-folder 12: 22)
    - 1935 (Box-folder 12: 23)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 12: 24)
  - Critical material, translations and other writings about Boris Pasternak (Box 13)
    - General
      - "Boris Pasternak - Ol'ga Freidenberg: Briefwechsel 1910-1954," Deutschlandfunk, Bücher im Gespräch, Typescript draft of radiobroadcast transcript, 1987 (Box-folder 13: 1)
      - "Boris Pasternak: Stikhi I proza," Novyi Mir, Printed copy, separatum, undated (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - Binyon, Michael, untitled draft for article to be published in The Sunday Times, Typescript, 1982 (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - Bräuer, Herbert, "Pasternaks Bedeutung als Dichter," Alma Mater Philippina, Printed copy, 1964 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Mallac, Guy de, "Pasternak and Marburg," The Russian Review, Printed copy, 1979 (Box-folder 13: 5)